Guide to the György Kepes papers M1796
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
György Kepes papers
1918-2010
1960-1990
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Kepes, Gyorgy
M1796
113 Linear Feet (108 boxes, 68 flat boxes, 8 cartons, 4 card boxes, 3 half-boxes, 2 map-folders, 1 tube)
The personal papers of artist, designer, and visual theorist György Kepes.
Biographical / Historical
Artist, designer, and visual theorist György Kepes was born in 1906 in Selyp, Hungary. Originally associated with Germany’s Bauhaus as a colleague of László Moholy-Nagy, he emigrated to the United States in 1937 to teach Light and Color at Moholy's New Bauhaus (soon to be called the Institute of Design) in Chicago. In 1944, he produced Language of Vision, a landmark book about design theory, followed by the publication of six Kepes-edited anthologies in a series called Vision + Value as well as several other books. In addition to being a prolific painter and photographer, Kepes relentlessly explored the various crossed paths between art and the sciences. In 1956, The New Landscape in Art and Science, an exhibition (and later book) focused on these interests, gathering scientific imagery including x-ray, infra-red, microscope and telescope photographs. Several original panels from this exhibition are present in the collection. Kepes began teaching at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology in 1947, first as an associate professor of visual design and becoming a full professor in 1949. As the first artist-in-residence, he encouraged collaboration between artists, designers, architects, and engineers by organizing seminars, workshops and exhibitions. In 1967 Kepes founded MIT's Center for Advanced Visual Studies (CAVS) and was its director until 1972, retiring two years later. Kepes died in 2001 at the age of 95.
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy. Selected video has been transferred and is available digitally.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased by Stanford University, Special Collections in 2010. Accessions 2010-186, 2011-058, and 2012-063.
Related Materials
The Archives of American Art holds the Gyorgy Kepes papers, 1825-1989: http://www.aaa.si.edu/collections/gyorgy-kepes-papers-725.
The Art Institute of Chicago holds the papers of Kepes' publisher Paul Theobold: Theobald, Paul, and Company Records, 1935-1988. http://digital-libraries.saic.edu/cdm/ref/collection/findingaids/id/14478
Scope and Contents
The Gyorgy Kepes collection contains manuscripts, typescripts, notes, research files, correspondence, photographs, slides & exhibition panels, artwork, catalogues, publications, media, and other material.
Art, Modern -- 20th century.; Design.; Hungarian-Americans; Photography.; Kepes, Gyorgy
- Series 1. Projects & designs
  - Sylvania Electric and Light Mobile chronology (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Scope and Contents
    Chronology of Kepes's Light Mobile project, correspondence between G. Kepes and Sylvania, and two tearsheets on Sylvania products.
  - Eastman Kodak Company correspondence re: Pan Am Building project (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Correspondence between G. Kepes and Eastman Kodak re: Kodak materials for Pan Am building commission.
  - Correspondence with Cyril Stanley Smith re: metals (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Details use of metals with "damascus" texture.
  - Sylvania Panelescent Lighting brochure (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Upper and Lower Falls Project (Box 17, Folder 8)
    Some of the material deals with remarks Kepes made about optimum utilization of the Falls in Rochester, New York. Much of the material is actually printed material that has appeared previously.
  - Times Square Project, 1969-1973 (Box 25, Folder 20)
    Correspondence and printed material about Kepes' Times Square project.
  - Times Square Clippings, 1973 (Box 25, Folder 21)
    New York Times clippings about Times Square Project, with letter to Kepes from Arnold H. Singal.
  - Tower of Light, 1964 (Box 25, Folder 22)
    Time, Cost, Coordination Estimates from architectural firm for Tower of Light.
  - Mobile Light Mural (Box 26, Folder 2)
    Typescript on the possiblity of a mobile light mural.
  - Paper scraps (Box 26, Folder 17)
    Paper scraps cut in various shapes and sizes - presumably for artistic usage.
  - Red Line (Box 27, Folder 26)
    Reproductions of several sheets of an abstract design.
  - Harvard Square Transit Project, 1981 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    Plans and printed material about Kepes' installation in the Harvard Square MBTA station.
  - Invoices and Bills, 1974, 1982 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    Bills related to exhibitions and sales.
  - Saint Mary's Cathedral, San Francisco, 1971 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    Two copies of Architectural Record article on Saint Mary's in San Francisco from September 1971.
  - Baltimore Road Project, 1974 (Box 28, Folder 30)
    Contains material about a proposed project for Baltimore.
  - Some Aspects of Image Generation and Manipulation for the Times Square Billboard Display System (Box 29, Folder 4)
    Manuscript of a report - names on it are Michael Polatnick and Kepes. Polatnick wrote it for a class, possibly with Kepes.
  - Harvard Square, 1985 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    Clipping and plan about Kepes' Harvard Square stained glass wall project.
  - KLM Mural, 1960 (Box 30, Folder 17)
    Correspondence and other documents related to a "Mobile Light Mural" Kepes did for the KLM building.
  - Miscellaneous material, 1970s-1980s (Box 30, Folder 21)
    Some correspondence and a contract with the Willet Stained Glass Studio from the Harvard Square Project. One photo.
  - Proposals for the Russell Street Corridor (Box 38, Folder 1)
    Document by Kepes for renewal proposals for the corridor between downtown Baltimore and Friendship (now Baltimore-Washington International) Airport along Russell Street. Airport was renamed in 1973, so this document predates 1973.
  - San Francisco Cathedral Design Correspondence, 1966-1973 (Box 38, Folder 2)
    Correspondence around Kepes' design of the glass in the main entrance of the St. Mary's Cathedral in San Francisco. Correspondents include, Kepes, artchitect McSweeney, Ryan & Lee, and the Archbishop of San Francisco Joseph T. McGucken.
  - G. Sterling Chapel Window, 1978 (Box 38, Folder 16)
    Correspondence regarding a window Kepes did for a chapel at the First and Second Church in Norfolk, Massachusetts.
  - Charles Center, 1962-1969 (Box 39, Folder 1)
    Correspondence, drawings, photographs, all relating to the Charles Center project in Baltimore.
  - Correspondence, New York City Fountain Project, 1969-1971 (Box 39, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence,Times Square, 1972-1973 (Box 39, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, Port Authority Panel, 1972 (Box 39, Folder 16)
  - Times Square Proposal, 1972 (Box 39, Folder 17)
    Corespondence and proposal.
  - Times Square, 1973-1974 (Box 39, Folder 18)
    Correspondence, clippings, printed material.
  - Mobile Light Mural (Box 58, Folder 4)
    Photocopy of an article.
  - Mobile Light Mural (Box 58, Folder 12)
    Photocopy of a typescript.
  - Kepes published art and design (Box 105, Folder 17)
  - Advisory Board of Printing and Advertising Clinics brochure [damaged] (Box 105, Folder 18)
  - "Illustration" pamphlet for Collins Miller & Hutchings, Inc. [damaged] (Box 105, Folder 19)
  - dust jacket galley for Roland H. Bainton's "Haunted Heretic" (Box 105, Folder 20)
  - dust jacket galley proofs- Beacon Press etc. (Box 190, Folder 2)
- Series 2. Photographs
  - 2.1. Photographs by or of Kepes work
    - Photographs by G. Kepes (Box 1, Folder 10)
      3 photographs signed Gyorgy Kepes, 2 with labels. Includes 1960 "Direction-Suggestion Linear Display," 1938 "Wall Graffito" of graffiti in Chicago, and 1940 "Motion Record."
    - Kepes negatives (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Mostly 3x4 negatives; slides, glass negative, and assorted uncut negatives in various formats.
      48 negatives in envelopes with label "FROM BOX NEGATIVES PAINTING;" 7 additional negatives, 3 additional slides, 1 additional glass negative. Negatives of works by Kepes, including documentation of paintings and stained glass, exhibition installation shots, and negatives for light studies and photographs. 1 small b/w photograph reproducing a Kepes painting.
    - Checklist by Nathan Lerner and Lloyd C. Engelbrecht (Box 27, Folder 25)
      Checklist of photographic prints by Kepes - notes that the prints were all made in 1972 and 1973, so those dates are probable.
    - Glass Slides (Box 40)
      Total of twenty-three glass lantern slides depicting Kepes' works. Originally together in a padded envelope. Individually wrapped in protective wrappers, placed in slide box.
    - Dad's paintings 1989, Slides, 1997-1999, Dad's Paintings for Hungary Orig. and Dupes, 1989-1999 (Box 41, Folders 1-6)
      Standard-size projection slides of Kepes' works. Originally in a plastic box with this label, all together in a padded envelope.
    - Gyorgy Kepes Paintings (Box 41, Folder 8)
      Originally in a box with this label. Photographic negatives. One polaroid.
    - Gyorgy Kepes, Untitled, 6' x 6', Private Collection negative (Box 41, Folder 14)
    - Gyorgy Kepes, Untitled, 4' x 4', Private Collection negative (Box 41, Folder 15)
    - Gyorgy Kepes, Untitled, 5' x 5' Neuberger Collection of American Art, NYC negative (Box 41, Folder 16)
    - Gyorgy Kepes, Untitled, 4' x 4', National Collection of Fine Arts, Washington, D.C. negative (Box 41, Folder 17)
    - Gy. K. Paintings Prints (Box 62, Folder 7)
      Originally in a box of this title. Contains not only prints, but also negatives and a few printed items.
    - Gy. K. Designs (Box 63, Folder 2)
      Originally in a box of this title. Photographic prints.
    - Gy.K. Paintings Photographs (Box 63, Folders 5-8)
      Originally in a box with this title. Also says "The New Landscape, 101-200," but the contents appear to be photos of paintings.
    - Gyorgy Kepes, Paintings, Negatives (Box 67, Folders 1-2)
      Originally in a box with this label. Also labeled N13. Also contains slips of paper with nearly unintelligible writing that seems to concern details of each shot. They were scattered throughout the box in no apparent order.
    - Photographs of G. Kepes Installations and Designs (Box 86, Folder 3)
    - Paintings and photographs G. Kepes (Box 86, Folder 4)
    - Photographs by G. Kepes (Box 86, Folder 5)
    - Kepes photographs, smaller oversized (Box 192, Folder 1)
      Two prints removed from Box 86, folders 5&6.
  - 2.2. Slides & negatives
    - Slides, c. 1970s (Box 106, Folder 1-2)
    - Slides, c. 1960s-1980s (Box 106, Folder 3)
    - Slides - Possibly Mexico, 1979-04 (Box 106, Folder 4)
    - Slides - Navarro Baldeweg, 1970s (Box 106, Folder 5)
    - Slides - Misc. (Box 106, Folder 6)
    - Slides, c. 1970s (Box 106, Folder 7)
    - Slides - Paintings at Shows (Box 106, Folder 8)
    - Slides, c. 1970s (Box 106, Folder 9)
    - Slides, c. 1950s-1970s (Box 106, Folder 10)
    - Slides- Misc. (Box 107, Folder 1-9)
    - Slides- Misc. (Box 108, Folder 1-9)
    - Slides- Misc. (Box 109, Folder 1-9)
    - Slides- Misc. (Box 110, Folder 1-5)
    - Negatives - Misc. (Box 110, Folder 6-11)
    - Negatives - Misc. (Box 111, Folder 1-4)
    - Negatives - Student Work (Box 111, Folder 5)
    - Cataloged Photographs, Incomplete Sequence (Box 111, Folder 6)
    - Negatives - BOS-BW-5 (Box 111, Folder 7)
    - Slides - Light Installation (Box 111, Folder 8)
    - Slides (Box 111, Folder 9)
    - Negatives, GK Paintings (Box 111, Folder 10)
    - Transparencies & Negatives - Works By Kepes (Box 111, Folder 11-12)
    - Slides in Carousels (Box 112)
    - Slides in Carousels (Box 113)
    - Slides in Carousels (Box 114)
    - Glass Slides - Student Works (Box 137)
    - Glass Slides - Student Works, Etc. (Box 138)
    - Glass Slides - Misc. (Box 139)
  - 2.3. Exhibition panels
    Large mounted photographs used for exhibition. Many are on masonite boards. At some point they were numbered 1-103 (although some numbered items that were not panels are filed elsewhere).
    - Light as a Creative Medium? Kepes photograms [34 & 35], c. 1940s (Box 141)
    - Light as a Creative Medium light study [30]; Kepes photogram c. 1930s [31] (Box 142)
    - Light as a Creative Medium?: Kepes photo? [32]; Kepes photogram c. 1940s [33] (Box 143)
    - Light as a Creative Medium?: Kepes photograph with magnetic filings [38]; Kepes photo [39] (Box 144)
    - Cover of Light as Creative Medium catalog, Kepes photo [36]; Kepes Radioshack mural [37] (Box 145)
    - Light as a Creative Medium or retrospective: Kepes photo with lenses [40]; Kepes photo [41] (Box 146)
    - Light as a Creative Medium or retrospective: Kepes photo [44]; Kepes photo [45] (Box 147)
    - Light as a Creative Medium or retrospective: Kepes photo [42]; Kepes photo [43] (Box 148)
    - Language of Vision: Lichtenberg Figures / Von Hippel; Cross-Section of Twig, 80x (Box 149)
    - Light as a Creative Medium?: lens distorted typography [25]; Moholy plexi sculpture? [59] (Box 150)
    - Light as a Creative Medium? Kepes light photo? [61 & 62] (Box 151)
    - Light as a Creative Medium? Kepes light photo? [69 & 72] (Box 152)
    - Light as a Creative Medium? Kepes photo liquid forms? [60]; ICA Boston retrospective? Kepes photo [68] (Box 153)
    - ICA Boston retrospective? Kepes photo [70 & 71] (Box 154)
    - Light as a Creative Medium? possible Kepes photos [58 & 63] (Box 155)
    - Marked ICA/K 34, Kepes photo with magnetic filings [74] (Box 156)
    - Light as a Creative Medium? Kepes photogram c. 1930s [29] (Box 157)
    - Marked ICA/K 32 Kepes photo [64] (Box 158)
    - Marked ICA/K 32 Kepes photo [66] (Box 159)
    - Kepes photo with water drops [48]; Urban Form Architectural Light exhibition panel. Fred Stone Reprographics [49]; repeat of exhibition panel from Urban Form and Artificial Light. Fred Stone Reprographics [52]; Kepes photo light reflections. Fred Stone Reprographics [56] (Box 160)
    - ICA Boston retrospective, possibly GK design for Bauhaus exhibition [26]; Kepes photo; water and screen. Fred Stone Reprographics [54]; Otto Piene posters/fliers. Fred Stone Reprographics [57]; ICA Boston retrospective? installation shot of Kepes design of UNESCO exhibition on housing c. 1948? [67] (Box 161)
    - Kepes photos, Fred Stone Reprographics [50, 51, 55]; work by Harold Tovish [53] (Box 162)
    - ICA Boston retrospective?: Kepes clock for daughter [27]; Kepes daughter jumping [28]; CAVS work by Harold Tovish. Fred Stone Reprographics [46]; Kepes screen photo, from Light as Creative Medium exhibition cover. Fred Stone Reprographics [47] (Box 163)
    - Marked ICA/K 39, Kepes photo [65] (Box 164)
    - ICA Boston retrospective probably Kepes photos. Punched holes, marked ICA [89, 90, 99, 101] (Box 165)
    - Boston aerial view, Fred Stone Reprographics [96]; Kepes photo? Fred Stone Reprographics [97]; Kepes photo (many copies of this image on various panels). Fred Stone Reprographics [98] (Box 166)
    - Kepes photo raindrops [75]; Kepes photo light pattern [76]; ICA Boston retrospective, Kepes photos, 4 punched holes, marked ICA [80 & 84] (Box 167)
    - ICA Boston retrospective, Kepes high speed photo, Two punched holes, marked ICA [85]; photo of splashing water. Two punched holes, marked ICA [86]; dauKepes high speed photo. Two punched holes, marked ICA [87] (Box 168)
    - ICA Boston retrospective?: Kepes photo daughters face? [73]; Kepes high speed photo. Fred Stone Reprographics [77]; Kepes daughter in house. Punched holes, marked ICA [78]; Kepes stroboscopic photo, Punched holes, marked ICA [79] (Box 169)
    - ICA Boston retrospective?: Kepes photo, 4 punched holes, marked ICA [81]; Kepes photo, 2 punched holes [82]; installation shot of Painter and the City, MIT Hayden Gallery 1950, design by Kepes. Punched holes, marked ICA [83]; CAVS, Harold Tovish reproduction, Fred Stone Reprographics [88] (Box 170)
    - ICA Boston retrospective?: Kepes photo, four punched holes, marked ICA [91]; installation shot of Art of United Nations, at Art Institute Chicago, designed and curated by Kepes, c. 1944. Punched holes, marked ICA [100]; installation shot of possibile New Bauhaus exhibition at MOMA possibly designed by Kepes. Punched holes, marked ICA [103] (Box 171)
    - New Landscape in Art and Science [11], 1951 (Box 172)
    - New Landscape in Art and Science [14], 1951 (Box 173)
    - New Landscape in Art and Science, tongue of deer [15], 1951 (Box 174)
    - Explorations: Wen-Ying Tsai, Cybernetic Sculpture [2]; Ted Kraynik, Video Luminar [3], 1970 (Box 175)
    - Explorations, Wen-Ying Tsai, Cybernetic Sculpture [6]; CAVS Mauricio Bueno, Environmental Ecology Tower [7], 1970 (Box 176)
    - New Landscape in Art and Science, Lichtenberg 1951 [19]; CAVS Peine, Environmental Pageantry [20] (Box 177)
    - New Landscape in Art and Science, "eutectic" compounds [23 & 24], 1951 (Box 178)
    - CAVS David Curt Morris, Light Cage [21]; New Landscape in Art and Science, 1951 [22] (Box 179)
    - New Landscape in Art and Science, Lichtenberg figure [12], 1951 (Box 180)
    - New Landscape in Art and Science [17 & 18], 1951 (Box 181)
    - CAVS?: Hiroo Kurano, student work [4]; Michio Ihara, Light Tower [5] (Box 182)
    - New Landscape in Art and Science [16], 1951 (Box 183)
    - New Landscape in Art and Science [1], 1951 (Box 184)
    - Explorations: installation shot [10]; Stan Vanderbeek computer graphic [13], 1970 (Box 185)
    - CAVS Kepes, Light walls for Boston Harbor [8 & 9] (Box 186)
  - 2.4. Miscellaneous photographs, slides, negatives
    Mostly scientific images and paintings. Some or all are produced by Kepes or used in projects.
    - Typography photographs (Box 1, Folder 3)
      5 photographs of typography and writing systems.
    - Unlabeled negatives (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Box of 130 negatives for reproduction in various Kepes publications but also other miscellaneous negatives. Note: images are not necessarily from Kepes's "Language of Vision" despite typed label on original Kodak photo box. Includes for example a negative of a New York Times Book Review article on Kepes's Vision + Value Series by Roger Jellinek. Some negatives include handwritten captions or citations on note, envelope, or negative; most reproduce images from other publications and include original text or caption copy in negative. Masking applied to some negatives in preparation for printing. Images include Balla painting, Futurist topography, Georges Seurat painting, diagrams from art and design textbooks, movement diagrams, Soviet posters, installation shot of design exhibition, and many others. Includes duplicates.
      Most 3x4 and 4x5; some smaller. Most contained in individual wax paper or manila envelopes.
    - Street signage photographs (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Approx. 9 x 10 and 9 x 9 black and white silver gelatin prints.
      3 photographs of American street signage; 2 specifically credited to Standard Oil Company.
    - Photographs of works by Frank Stella and Kenneth Noland (Box 1, Folder 6)
      4 photographs of artworks, one catalog or journal tearsheet with Frank Stella lithograph marked.
    - Scientific photographs (Box 1, Folder 7)
      19 photographs of patterns found in science. Image probably relate to or were published in The New Landscape in Art and Science or other Kepes publications. Includes radiograph, "fluid mapper pattern," Lissajous figures, Bell Telephone Laboratory diagram, and similar images.
    - KINSYN Laserphoto, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      4 x 5 black and white glossy silver gelatin prints.
      July 1973 "MIT Reports on Research" newsletter with article on KINSYN computer system and Laserphoto images, and 10 photographs of Laserphoto output.
    - P. Xagozazis Hewlett-Packard plotter photographs (Box 1, Folder 9)
      4 photographs showing patterns produced by P. Xagozazis on Hewlett-Packard 9810A and 11215A plotters. Includes 3 unidentified small photographs found in sleeve with other images.
    - Ceramics and pottery photographs (Box 1, Folder 11)
      2 photographs of pottery from Peabody Museum, Harvard University.
    - Miscellaneous photographs from 1960s and 1970s (Box 1, Folder 12)
      5 photographs identified from 1960s, including student work from M.I.T. Visual Design Course and Light and Color Course, photograph of exhibition poster for show at the Hayden Gallery in 1973 for MIT CAVS fellow Friedrich St. Florian, and still from Stan Vanderbeek film.
    - Photographs of architectural diagrams, perspective diagrams, visual illusions, and human anatomy (Box 1, Folder 13)
      27 photographs, mostly unlabeled, of architectural diagrams, visual and optical illusions, human anatomy diagrams, images illustrating perspectival systems, and Gestalt psychology diagrams. Includes one additional tearsheet from catalog or journal of 1922 L. Peri linoleum cut.
    - Exhibition installation shots (Box 1, Folder 14)
      2 photographs showing The Family of Man at the Museum of Modern Art and a December 1946 Mondrian exhibition.
    - Design photographs (Box 1, Folder 15)
      3 photographs including an Olivetti typewriter, a Paul Rand cover design for "Origins of Modern Sculpture" by W.R. Valentiner, and a dapping die from the Museum of Modern Art.
    - Engineering photographs (Box 1, Folder 16)
      2 photographs include an American Airlines aircraft and the interior of the National Linear Accelerator.
    - photographs of Cubist, futurist, and collage works (Box 1, Folder 17)
      7 photographs of works by Pablo Picasso, Balla, Robert Delaunay, Juan Gris, and Schwitters.
    - photographs of Impressionist and post-Impressionist works (Box 1, Folder 18)
      4 photographs of works by Claude Monet, Cezanne, Gauguin, and Matisse.
    - Julius Shulman photographs of Richard Neutra houses (Box 1, Folder 19)
      2 photographs by Julius Shulman of homes designed by Richard Neutra.
    - photographs of Russian avant-garde works (Box 1, Folder 20)
      5 photographs of works by El Lissitzky and others.
    - Signed Edmund Teske photograph (Box 1, Folder 21)
      4 x 6 black and white silver gelatin print, signed in blue pencil on back.
      Photograph of St. Louis Fish Market storefront
    - Saul Bass graphic design stills (Box 1, Folder 22)
      3 photographs depicting Saul Bass graphic design for film, including the intro sequence to Psycho.
    - Unidentified and unlabeled photographs (Box 1, Folder 23)
      21 photographs with no labels.
    - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 1, Folder 24)
      31 photographs of works by Laszlo Moholy-Nagy, Louise Nevelson, Oskar Kokoschka, Ambrozio Lorenzetti, Whistler, Turner, Alberto Giacometti, Joan Miro, Jean Dubuffet, Fritz Glarner, Richard Lohse, Toshihiro Katayama, Francis Haar, Eduardo Chillida, Marcel Duchamp, Viking Eggeling, Herbert Bayer, and others. Includes two postcards from the British Museum.
    - Miscellaneous photographs 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      42 photographs of works by Jean Arp, Rodchenko, Marcel Duchamp, Poussin, Malevich, Giacometti, and others. Photographs of an Underwood typewriter, neolithic cave drawings, MIT course photograph; also includes 6 Gestalt diagrams printed directly on card stock. Note: images are not necessarily from a particular publication despite box labels.
    - Miscellaneous photographs 2 (Box 2, Folder 2)